<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Ayiko’s Awful Opinions</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Ayiko's blog about software and whatnot.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 03:00:33 EAT</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 03:00:33 EAT</lastBuildDate>
    <ttl>60</ttl>

    
    <item>
      <title>Yet Another Advice for Engineering College Students</title>
      <link>/yet-another-advice-for-engineering-college-students.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<div><span class="date">11th Mar 2021</span><h2>Yet Another Advice for Engineering College Students</h2><p>Hi. Today (or whatever day you are reading this—even tomorrow), 
I’m going to give tech students advice. Chances are you want to get 
the right advice as a student. (Unless you fear that I would hate 
you forever if you didn’t read my blog.) Well, you’ve come to the 
right place, but first a review of one of my past daydreams.</p><p>When I was a teenager (or was it in my early 20s?), as soon as I 
got admitted to study Telecommunications in <a href="https://kyu.ac.ug">KYU</a>
, I was convinced that by the end of the four-year course, I’ll be 
busy making very important decisions in the Switching Centre of either 
<a href="https://mtn.co.ug">MTN</a> or <a href="https://airtel.co.ug">Airtel</a>. 
Heck, I could imagine my self deciding whose calls go through and 
whose get dropped (especially those from schools who beat 
<a href="http://ombacicollege.ac.ug">ST. JOSCOOM</a> in football games 
when I was still there) while eating 
<a href="https://observer.ug/businessnews/57631-ugandans-should-borrow-a-leaf-from-dennis-aliga">Nang-Nang</a>
, especially for brunch. A lot of my daydreams in those days involved 
Nang-Nang.</p><p><a href="https://www.monitor.co.ug/uganda/magazines/farming/nang-nang-fish-puts-more-money-in-the-pocket-1837150" title="CC Daily Monitor: Nang-Nang"><img src="/static/img/nang-nang-fish.jpg" style="max-width: 95%;" /></a></p><p>Towards the end of the second year, I realised that all was not 
going according to plan. So I started seeking career advice.  Believe 
me, dear reader, when I suggest that getting the right advice as a 
student is a pain in the neck, especially in the field of computer 
science and engineering . When I had first encountered a (holding nose 
between thumb and forefinger) “Telecom Engineer”, I was not prepared 
for some of the preternatural concepts he threw at me as part of his 
advice. Most of the people I sought advice from resorted to obfuscation 
when confronted with sharp questions. At my first job ( rather graduate 
training) I noticed how many things there are that many engineering 
departments are too snooty to actually teach you just because they 
consider them to be  “vocational” but not academic.</p><p>Anyway. Back to my advice. (Aw, do we have to talk about <em>that</em>
 again? I was enjoying that brief digression into freshman daydreams.) 
Over the last eleven or so months, a few students did occasionally call 
and message me asking for career advice even though schools were closed. 
Since most of them have reported back for studies, I thought I’d write  
up my basic non-technical advice which they can read, laugh at, and 
ignore.</p><p>A warning though; I, too, have no idea what I’m talking about when I 
give advice to students. I’m so hopelessly out of date that I’m not hip 
and cool and trendy and all about the latest technology, but rather a 
retro lover. I’m still wearing my disco pants (I’ve never stayed more 
alive than I was in 1997! 
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ETzJwQlXTsE&amp;list=OLAK5uy_lDJQk9B5sQ4NsKh1NepLYNddyckV4kRYo">LOI</a> 
was our national anthem). So you’d be better off ignoring what I’m saying 
here and go do something better with your life.</p><p>So where were we? Ah, yes! Advice.</p><p>Without further ado, Here’s my three-pronged advice for you (worth 
what you paid for them):</p><ol><li>Learn to write and talk before graduating.</li><li>Learn microeconomics before gradating.</li><li>Invest regularly in your knowledge portfolio.</li></ol><p>Yes! That’s it. So, what did you expect? Something long, hairy, and 
complicated? Now, take a seat, buddy, and prepare for enlightenment.<p><h3>1. Learn to write and talk before graduating.</h3><p>Bwa ha ha ha ha! It seems like this is not really advice. If that 
made any sense at all, you’re probably already a member of 
<a href="https://ugandayouthwriting.org">Uganda Youth Creative Writing</a>, 
and if it didn’t, you probably think I’m dumb because you’ve been 
writing notes and exams since your early school years. Well, it might not 
be significant, but I’m telling you this for three reasons:</p><ul><li>It bit me in the ass the first time I had to write a service 
      manual.</li><li>In most companies, employees with the most power and influence 
      are the ones who can write and speak in English clearly, 
      convincingly, and comfortably.</li><li>It’s not really a problem. You can work around it.</li></ul><p>Most graduates who come out, and they’ve got degrees in engineering or 
computer science, writing’s not their strong point. It’s actually very 
difficult to teach because it’s very individual. Somebody has got to take 
your text and a red pen and explain to you what you did wrong. And that’s 
very time consuming.</p><p>Having the best ideas and the most pragmatic thinking is ultimately 
sterile unless you can communicate with other people. You’ll find your self 
in situations where you’ve to write proposals, memos requesting and 
justifying resources, reporting status, …etc., so you need to do it well.</p><p>How can you learn to write? My suggestions, which you will no doubt 
accept because I’m the one writing the text, is to start a journal and take 
those write intensive course units seriously, that is those in which you write 
an awful lot to pass them. The more you write, the easier it will be, and the 
easier it is to write, the more you’ll write, in a virtuous circle.</p><h3>2. Learn microeconomics before gradating.</h3><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microeconomics">Microeconomics</a> 
is actually about studying the behaviour of individuals and 
firms in making decisions regarding the allocation of scarce resources and the 
interactions among these individuals and firms. Please study it if you 
haven’t already. And feel free to leave the macroeconomics stuff (unless you’re 
studying to be the governor of the central bank of your country) provided you 
promise to take Microeconomics.</p><p>Am coercing you to make promises, which you must fulfil otherwise you’ll get me 
to stop liking you,  because you have to know about supply and demand, you have 
to know about competitive advantage, and you have to understand NPVs and 
discounting and marginal utility before you’ll have any idea why business works 
the way it does.</p><img class="right" src="/static/img/swiss-knife.png" width="250" height="210" title="Who wants this clumsy stuff!" /><p>I’ve personally seen engineers with crazy ideas that make sense in engineering 
but don’t make sense in capitalism. The classical mistake many engineers make is 
spending months building something nobody wants. So if you understand this stuff, 
you’re more valuable to a company than a fellow engineer who doesn’t grok it. 
Period!</p><h3>3. Invest regularly in your knowledge portfolio.</h3><p>In <a href="https://pragprog.com/titles/tpp20/the-pragmatic-programmer-20th-anniversary-edition/">The Pragmatic Programmer (David T &amp; Andrew H, 2019)</a>
, the authors say “Your knowledge and experience are your most important 
day-to-day professional assets. Unfortunately, they’re <em>expiring 
assets</em>”.</p><p>Knowledge becomes out of date as new techniques, languages, and environments 
are developed. Also the ever changing market forces may render experience 
obsolete or irrelevant. With the ever-increasing pace of change in our 
technological society, this can happen pretty quickly. As the value of your 
knowledge declines, so does your value to your company or client. We want to 
prevent this from ever happening.</p><p>Alert readers will be wondering, “how do I learn how to learn, and how do I 
know what to learn?” Well, the authors go on to say that managing a knowledge 
portfolio is very similar to managing a financial portfolio:</p><ol><li>Serious investors invest regularly—as a habit.</li><li>Diversification is the key to long-term success.</li><li>Smart investors balance their portfolios between conservative and high-risk, 
high-reward investments.</li><li>Investors try to buy low and sell high for maximum return.</li><li>Portfolios should be reviewed and rebalanced periodically.</li></ol><p>Therefore, to be successful in your career, you must invest in your knowledge 
portfolio using these same guidelines. That’s the bad news about IT and engineering 
disciplines.</p><p>The good news is that managing this kind of investment isn’t an innate talent 
that people are born with—it can be learned just like any other skill. The trick 
is to make yourself do it initially and form a habit (develop a routine which you 
follow). And then, one day, finally, perhaps when it’s too late, you’ll wake up and 
say, “Hmm. Maybe I’ll never know how to manage my knowledge portfolio.” And on that 
day only, and not three seconds before, but on that day and from that day forward, 
your brain will have internalized and you’ll find yourself sucking up new knowledge 
automatically. In the meantime, all is not lost: you still have my blessing if you 
still want to eat Nang-Nang.</p><div class="note"><h3>NOTE</h3><p>If you follow my advice, you, too, may end up selling stock in 
<a href="https://www.allianceinmotion.com/home">AIM Global</a> way too soon, 
turning down jobs at <a href="https://mtn.co.ug">MTN</a> because you want 
your own office with a door, and other stupid life decisions, but they won’t 
be my fault. I told you not to listen to me.</p></div></p></p></div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 03:00:33 EAT</pubDate>
      <guid>/yet-another-advice-for-engineering-college-students.html</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, Saucy World!</title>
      <link>/hello-saucy-world.html</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<div><span class="date">30th Oct 2020</span><h2>Hello, Saucy World!</h2><img class="left" src="/static/img/hello-world.png" width="140" height="90" style="margin-top: 1.2em" title="Let’s get blogy, blogy, I wanna get blogy..." /><p style="margin-top: 2.3em;">
   Trying to solve more problems than I cause.<br />
   When I’m happy, I love technology. Sometimes I feel sad.
</p></div>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 13:25:07 EAT</pubDate>
      <guid>/hello-saucy-world.html</guid>
    </item>
    
 
  </channel>
</rss>

